this video is part two of my review of
the walthers mainline sw7 in illinois
central golf
this video i'm going to do a dcc decoder
install as well as speaker installations
so let's go ahead and jump into it
so just for simplicity's sake i'm only
going to show you one locomotive in the
video but i'm going to do both of these
simultaneously
so these were these locomotives the
walthers mainline are dcc ready and they
have the new next 18 plug-in which
ironically up until about a month ago
this is uh it's august of 2021.
the nmra national model railroad
association
actually just approved the the next 18
as
as an approved nmra standard for dcc
decoder so
kind of cool that this just was approved
by the nmra so this is a fairly new
plug-in
for a dcc decoder
the supplies you're going to need to do
this certainly you're going to need your
decoder
this is a personal preference
i've leaned more towards esu over the
tsunamis lately
you'll need a speaker
i'm going to talk about speakers here as
i get into the the operations but i
purchased this from scale sound systems
it's not shown in the video right now
but i'm going to need to solder these to
the decoder board so you'll need your
soldering equipment some wire to take
care of that some double sided tape to
get the
speaker secured and
that's all you'll need
here's a close-up of the speaker and i
just want to spend just a minute or two
here talking about this
by no means is this a paid endorsement
or anything
but i have found there is a company
called scale sound systems
the gentleman who owns its name is jt
burke
he does a phenomenal job he builds these
speakers themselves
they're depending on what type of
locomotive you're getting they're about
12 to 14 dollars per speaker
and the nice thing is he builds them per
the specifications of what's going to
fit within the model so
this particular speaker here is
absolutely designed specifically for the
walthers emd sw7 so
even though i haven't had the shell off
the locomotive yet
i know that i'm not going to fight with
getting the speaker to fit because it is
already designed for that
so
his jt's website is in
you'll see it on the bottom of the
screen here it's also in my description
you can purchase the speakers and do
self installations actually got the
decoders from him as well by the way
so you can purchase it and do it
yourself or you can mail your locomotive
in which i did that with one of my
gp9s the original illinois central gp9
it was a
afternoon genesis from about 2012. it
had an original tsunami one decoder in
it
um it had
incandescent bulbs i milled it into jt
he put a low sound five minute keep
alive in it upgraded the led the lights
to leds
i just did a phenomenal job so
i highly highly recommend jt i i
purchase from him and he's not a sponsor
or anything so it's not a paid
endorsement it's just my opinion he's a
good guy he's great for the for our
hobby
and just real quick as i mentioned it
when i was talking about speakers
you can get decoders from jt as well
so this is again it's a it's an esu
luxon 5.
the number on this is 58828
you can purchase this as a blank decoder
would i mean that's how they come it's a
blank decoder
so if you don't have a low programmer a
lot of the um hobby shops that you can
purchase these from will actually
program them for you so this is already
programmed for nsw 7. once i get it
installed i'll walk through the process
of how you would
install the sound file on here if you if
you purchased it directly as a blank
decoder but jt was nice enough to
pre-load these
with with the sw7 sound so
they're out of the box going to be ready
to go for me okay so it's time to take
the shell off and
there's a couple things i want to point
out to you
so this particular locomotive
are tabs there's
two on each side here
there's two here and then one at the
back
this one you don't have to take any of
the couplers off you don't have to
unscrew anything it's basically those
plastic snap clips
the whole hood including the cab comes
off
so because this handrail is attached to
the frame
we on both sides we just sort of have to
gently loosen that
to make sure that it doesn't get caught
up on anything
and now basically
you just have to
gently the work the shell off
so
don't force it
um i know your tendency is to try to
force it
just have to be gentle and careful and
take your time with this so
i'm going to move the camera out of the
way so i get a better angle on this but
i'm going to
basically just wiggle this off here and
it'll get us access to the the board
okay i got the
tabs loose
so this whole piece just slides off
and you can see
there is
the wires for the um the rear led light
here's the front light and then here's
your board
so a couple things i want to draw your
attention to
so here's the headlight
um
this board right here is your um the dc
jumper that we're going to take off and
this has a next 18 plug on it
here you have your
power feeds coming in
this simple wire job you got a front and
rear led light
so two wires per light
so here is like i said here's your
jumper board
and then i'm going to show you a couple
of cool things here now one of the
things i didn't realize because i never
had a walthers main line
that i did a dcc conversion on
there's actually a one millimeter micro
plug here
that is for the speaker
i was thinking that i was going to have
to wire the speaker directly to the dcc
decoder but since we
have this little port on here
it's kind of making installing this
locomotive or the speaker on this
locomotive pretty simple i'm just going
to run two wires
to a one millimeter micro and plug it in
there
so here's the other really really cool
thing and i said i um use scale sound
speakers
and i ordered it specifically for
walther zestabira um sw7
so
this
enclosure here is where the speaker goes
i don't know how you can see it on the
camera there's four screws holding this
in
there's a cradle for the led
so
scale sounds manufactured these where i
can pull this box off
screw the speaker on
has the cradle for the led
so everything's going to fit nice and
neatly underneath the shell of the
locomotive so
that made this well worth purchase price
to make this wiring job a little easier
so
what i'm going to do
before i start disassembling the
locomotive i'm just going to get
my soldering iron out and we'll get the
feeders off of here so this is ready to
go and then we'll go ahead and get it
installed so here's what the micro plug
looks like
again one millimeter
you can get these pretty much anywhere
amazon has um
scale sound speakers sells them as well
so
just make sure if you're going to do
this job to go ahead and get one of
these
so
just real quick i got my solder here
i'm gonna go ahead and just i'm gonna
tin these real quick and i'll go ahead
and get them on the speaker
okay so you can see this has the
the red so i'm going to go ahead
and solder the red
wire
to that lead
so
there we go so this is
wired and ready to go now we're gonna
remove the uh
just this enclosure here so there's a
piece of
scotch tape on here i'm just going to
grab my
blade
and get underneath it here a little bit
i'm going to just sort of gently peel
this off i'm going to save it because
i'm going to
use it to
connect these wires back when i'm done
or secure the wires i should say
and if you ruin it you ruin it you get a
new piece of tape
okay so we get this pulled off
i'm just gonna set this off to the side
here
so now the led we don't even have to
unwire it
we'll just let that move that out of the
way and then there's just four
[Music]
phillips heads and two of these heads
are actually below
the
um
the board here so i'm gonna have to
unscrew the board there's a screw right
here and i should be able to get access
to it so
i'm going to shut the camera off i will
show you before i take this off so give
me one second okay i wanted to show you
this
so there's actually two screws
holding the the
board in place there's one back here and
there was one right here
so i just undid this one and then you
can just gently
sort of slide this out of the way
and that's going to get you access to
these other two screws so i'm going to
pull these off here real quick
and then this piece comes out we just
have to be careful of those two pickups
and we're good to go so the nail that i
got this was the piece that was on here
and i just wanted to show you
it is
pretty much a perfect fit so i can
ensure
the shell will go back on just fine
overlay the two
you can see the screw holes
line up perfectly so shouldn't have any
trouble getting this installed
one of the things i will
show you real quick here is
sorry what i was saying at the end of
that last
segment was
when we set this on here we want to make
sure these
the power pickups are
connected but before
i actually put the board back in place
i have to plug this micro port in
because once this is slid back
i'm not going to have very much
clearance so i'm going to go ahead and
get this
i'm gonna get a couple screws in i think
and then i'll go ahead and plug that in
and get it
set ready to go okay so i got the
speaker
the first two screws in what i'm gonna
do before i put the last ones in i'm
gonna get
the led
back where i want it or where it belongs
because i want to make sure that the
wires for
the headlight
are where i need them to be
before i mess
with the speaker lights here so i'm just
going to take that piece of tape
just be real careful
get that tape back down in there
okay so those are where
i want them to be here's my
speaker wire and i'm just going to
carefully plug it into this port here
there it goes
i'm gonna gently
make sure those are intact okay i'm
gonna get these last two screws in and
i'm gonna get the board back in place
got those last two screws in
now i'm just gonna
reconnect my
board here
with this tiny little screw
and we have successfully got the speaker
installed
and then we got the the lights back
and everything ready to go for
the speaker so as i mentioned before i'm
going to use the loch sound 5
and
it's a luxon 5 micro
and it's next 18 so let's go ahead and
pull this out of the box again
as i mentioned earlier
generally you can get these blank
and then program them if you have a low
programmer or a lot of dealers will
actually program them for you you just
have to tell them what sound file they
want
i'm gonna go ahead and
pull this out here
so
it's a micro decoder so it's real small
and then right here is the next 18 plug
so i'm going to get this stuff out of
the way and i'll zoom in and show you
how to change out the decoder so this
part's pretty easy
the main thing is just make sure
that you plug
the decoder in the direct correct
direction and this one is actually
pretty simple so i'm going to pull out
the dc jumper here
and you can i'm going to flip it over as
i take it out
so here is
the plug
so i'm just going to flip my decoder
over so you can see
they're both running the same direction
i'm just going to take this little lok
sound 5 micro
and just plug it right in there
make sure it seeds
there we go
and it's installed and we're ready to
put the shell back on the locomotive
okay you can see i got the
hood and everything reinstalled
looks great
i didn't damage it too much it was a
little bit of a struggle
and also while i was doing this one i
did the other locomotive
1203 so i got both of these
um
speakers installed and decoders
installed
so now let's go ahead and get the test
track out and let's test these things
out and make sure they work
okay you can see i've got my test layout
here so again ordinarily
if you would have bought these decoders
blank
which is pretty much how they come
unless you have your
dealer preload the sound for you
we'd move into
the third part of this video where i'd
show you how to program
the decoders
i'm still going to do that even though
these are already programmed but since
they're programmed i just want to verify
real quick that
everything is installed properly the
speakers are working the lights work the
decoder responds so i'm just going to
grab
12.03 here
drop it on the
track here
and we'll go ahead and give it a quick
test
okay so let's go ahead and hit track
power
and
this is default address three so i'll
hit my
default address three first thing i'm
going to do is i'm going to put it in
forward direction
check the front light by pressing f0
you have to take my word for just a
little bit you can kind of see the side
lights here let's go ahead and reverse
it
you can see that they both work i'll
verify it works
even though i'm not going to move the
angle of the camera so
do a couple other quick sound functions
bell works
horn works
initiate startup sequence
[Applause]
give a little throttle
okay
so we successfully installed the speaker
and the decoder so we converted this
locomotive from a dc c
ready but it was a dc locomotive
i got a lok sound five in it and this
was for me is a little bit it's
obviously a little bit of work
but to not have to pay for
uh the dcc and sound that walther was
offering with the essential sound unit
decoder that i probably would have
swapped out anyway i was able to save
about sixty five dollars
getting the dc only version i invested
right at about a hundred dollars i think
between the decoder and the speaker is
look right at a hundred dollars so i
have a great sounding locomotive
i'm going to stop the video here i'm
going to test 1206 real quick
make sure that works then we'll jump
into part 3.
so here's 1206
again default address three
go ahead and apply track power
headlight
front you can tell it's on
rear you can tell it's on
do a startup sequence here
[Applause]
give it a little bit of throttle
so
[Applause]
perfect they both work so this
installation was successful
thank you for watching part two of my
review so i'm gonna go ahead and jump
into part three
part three will be
basically how you would program the
decoder and it is using the esu local
programmer so if you don't have a low
programmer it's really hard to
install sound files while it's
impossible to stall some sound file
files if you don't have the log sound
decoder
or the look programmer i mean so
stay tuned for part three
we'll
go ahead and
work on this on the look programmer and
i'll do a full sound demonstration with
it so
thanks for watching part two and
we'll hopefully see you back soon